I'm here to answer two very important
questions. What happens when we give
Bellow Bard of Brambles a rocket? And
what happens when we turn them into a
skeleton? Now, before we get into this,
you better believe we're going to be
talking about layers. You ready for the
quick layers recap?
>> Three.
>> Here we go.
>> 2 1 go.
>> Layers are the order in which we apply
multiple continuous effects to a board
state. Continuous effects are effects
that would change the printed
information on a card, like turning an
artifact into a creature and setting its
power and toughness, or simply copying
something with a clone. There are seven
types of effects, also known as layers,
and we apply them in order of the layers
list from top to bottom. I'm about to
oversimplify these for the sake of the
video, but the three most important
layers rules to understand is one,
layers are constantly checked and
applied. If anything happens in the
game, the layers are instantly checked
and reapplied. two for the effects on
the same layer. In most cases, we apply
them in timestamp order. Basically, the
order in which they entered play. And
three, if a single effect impacts one
layer or a block of text impacts
multiple layers, if part of that effect
starts applying before it gets removed
in layer 6, it will continue to apply.
This will be important for later.
Now, with that out of the way, what
happens when we have Bellow in play with
one of the seven spacecrafts from Edge
of Eternities?
Let's say we have the Dawn Sire Sunstar
Dreadnaugh in play. What would it look
like with no charge counters on it with
Bellow? And what would it look like with
20 charge counters on it with Bellow? As
a reminder, Bellow Bard of Brambles
says, "During your turn, each
non-equipment artifact and each non-ora
enchantment you control with mana value
four or greater is a 44 elemental
creature in addition to its other types
and has indestructible haste. And
whenever this creature deals combat
damage to a player, draw a card." And if
you've watched one of my other Bellow
videos before, you'll know Bellow's
ability impacts layers 4, 6, and 7. Now,
let's take a closer look at a
spacecraft.
Currently, all spacecrafts have the
station keyword, and they either have
one or two station symbols. The station
ability allows you to tap creatures and
add a number of charge counters on the
spacecraft equal to that creature's
power. So, if Dawn sire was in play with
no charge counters on it and we played
Bellow, I think we can all agree that
Dawnire would become a 44 legendary
artifact creature, spacecraft elemental
with indestructible haste. And whenever
this creature deals combat damage to a
player, draw a card. And while the
spacecraft has no counters on it, these
other abilities here don't exist, right?
Or do they?
So, this is one of those situations
where we actually need to take a look
under the hood, so to speak, and check
what the comprehensive rules says about
station. Jumping to section 721, which
covers station, the two rules we care
about are 721.2A
and 721.2b,
which tells us that station abilities
read like this. As long as this
permanent has n or more charge counters,
it has these abilities.
And as long as this permanent has n or
more charge counters on it, it has these
abilities and is a creature with base
power and toughness as marked in
addition to its other types. So
effectively, these spacecrafts look like
this.
meaning that these two static abilities
are going to be applying a continuous
effect to the spacecraft as soon as they
enter play.
One thing I want to clarify, both the
spacecraft's continuous effects and
Bellow's ability don't ever turn off, so
to speak. While Bellow's ability only
applies during your turn and the station
abilities are only applied once the
spacecraft reaches a certain amount of
charge counters, both of these effects
timestamps are tied to the card itself
and are constantly checking to see if
you get the additional effects or not.
Think of them like a TV on standby.
So, if we had a spacecraft that was
fully stationed and bellow in play, the
only part we need to focus on is the
power and toughness side of things. And
it's really simple. We just apply the
power and toughness setting effects in
time stamp order. If bellow was in play
first, we set the spacecraft to be a 44
and then we would apply the spacecraft's
power and toughness setting effect.
However, if the spacecraft was in play
first, the end result, no matter if the
spacecraft was fully stationed or not,
it would be a 44. Again, this doesn't
change if the spacecraft becomes fully
stationed after Bellow enters play. We
apply the continuous effects in
timestamp order, which is tied to the
card itself.
Next, what would happen if Bellow got
reanimated by Zoo Eat Osteo Harmonist?
Now, if you were paying attention to the
start of the video, you should already
know the answer to this question. Let's
quickly review Zoo. They say, "Tap
return target creature from your
graveyard to the battlefield. It's a
skeleton in addition to its other types
and has no abilities. Activate only as a
sorcery.
So there's two layers that zoo impacts
here. We have a layer 4 type changing
effect here giving the skeleton car
type. And next we have a removal of
abilities here. So that applies in layer
six. So we resurrect Bellow with Zoo.
Now let's go down the layers list and
apply the layers. Now, there's a new
layers rule with the release of Edge of
Eternities 613.7N
that we quickly need to cover. I'll talk
about this in more detail in another
video, but all you need to know is that
thanks to this rule, Zoo's continuous
effects will be applied to Bellow last.
We'll start at layer 4. Bellow makes
artifacts and enchantments creature
elementals, and Zoo makes Bellow a
skeleton.
We then move to layer six. Bellow gives
the artifacts and enchantments,
indestructible haste, and whenever this
creature deals combat damage to a
player, draw a card. And then Zoo
removes all abilities from Bellow. Now,
as we've mentioned before, thanks to
rule 613.6, Six. If an effect starts to
apply in one layer and or sub layer, it
will continue to be applied to the same
set of objects in each other applicable
layer and or sub layer even if the
ability generating the effects is
removed during this process. So even
though bellow will have no abilities at
this point, we still continue to apply
their continuous effect.
Finally, we move to layer 7B and set the
artifacts and enchantments power and
toughness to 44.
So, we end up with a bellow with no
abilities and is a skeleton, but all
artifacts and enchantments with mana
value four or greater will still be
creatures during your turn.
So, there we go. Another set, another
weird bellow interaction. Have you got
any more for me? As always, be sure to
like the video if you learned something
and subscribe because if you don't, I'll
send Bellow to the next eternity.
Thanks for watching and I'll see you in
the next one.